Guide to the Time Inc. Discover Publishing and Business Records: Publisher Bruce Barnet Files 1980-1987 MS 3009-RG 43
New-York Historical Society
Time Inc. Discover Publishing and Business Records: Publisher Bruce Barnet Files
1980-1987
New-York Historical Society
Time, inc.
MS 3009-RG 43
1.25 Linear feet in 2 record cartons
Publisher Bruce Barnet's files document the final review of feasibility of the popular science magazine Discover and its sale.
Conditions Governing Access
Open to qualified researchers with the exception of restricted materials. Restricted materials include contracts, personnel files, and records with personally identifiable information. Restricted materials are located in box R17.
Materials in this collection are stored offsite. For more information on making arrangements to consult them, please visit www.nyhistory.org/library/visit.
Arrangement
Organized alphabetically. All files but the Science 86 Acquisition binder were found together. Alphabetical arrangement was imposed.
Historical Note
The popular science magazine Discover was created via task force outside of the Magazine Development Group and first published in 1980. Time Inc. sold Discover to Family Media, Inc. in 1987.
For the majority of Time Inc.'s existence, the company maintained a strict separation of editorial from the publishing and business side of each magazine, colloquially called the separation of "church" (editorial) and "state" (publishing). Publishing and Business Management includes the publisher, general manager, business manager, advertising sales, marketing services, letters, circulation, and public relations. Cofounder Henry Luce structured Time Inc. this way so that the business side could not (in theory) influence the editorial content of the publications. For example, the advertising sales people could not interfere with a magazine's decision to run an article on the dangers of cigarette smoking, even though it might mean losing millions of dollars in tobacco ads.
Biographical Note
Bruce Barnet was final Circulation Director of Life. He also held positions with Time-Life Films, Fortune publishing, and the Magazine Development Group (MDG) publishing. After serving in the MDG, the Discover board appointed him as publisher specifically to "take a hard look at the business potential for the magazine." Ultimately Barnet recommended in a report to the board that Time Inc. sell Discover. After the 1987 sale, Barnet was promoted to Vice President of Planning for the Magazine Group.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of Time Inc. in 2015.
Related Materials
This finding aid relates to just one record group of the Time Inc. Records. For information about the other record groups and for overall information about the archives, please see the Guide to the Time Inc. Records (MS 3009). The Henry Luce Papers (MS 3014) were acquired with the Time Inc. Records. The collection of books acquired with the records are cataloged as the Time Inc. Reference Library.
Information about the history of Discover and additional records from the editorial or publishing offices can be found in the Time Inc. Subject Files (MS 3009-RG 1) and the Time Inc. Annex Files (MS 3009-RG 39).
Scope and Contents
Publisher Bruce Barnet's files document the final review of feasibility of Discover and its sale. The records include reports on finances and circulation, memoranda on options, press releases, crafted question and answers to use after the announcement, and personnel issues.
Corporations -- History.; Corporations -- New York (State) -- New York.; Publishers and publishing -- New York (State) -- New York.; Corporation records.; Organization files.; Time, inc. -- Archives.; Time, inc. -- History.; Barnet, Bruce
- General, 1987 (Offsite-box 3753, Folder 1)
- General [RESTRICTED], 1987 (Offsite-box R17)
- Address List, 1987 (Offsite-box 3753, Folder 2)
- Ad Sales, 1987 (Offsite-box 3753, Folder 3)
- Asset Purchase Agreement [RESTRICTED], 1987 (Offsite-box R17)
- Board Meetings, 1986-1987 (Offsite-box 3753, Folder 4-5)
- Brack, Reginald Meeting, 1987 March 12 (Offsite-box 3753, Folder 6)
- Budget, 1987 (Offsite-box 3753, Folder 7-8)
- Final Intent Letter: Family Media, 1987 (Offsite-box 3753, Folder 9)
- Final Intent Letter Family Media [RESTRICTED], 1987 (Offsite-box R17)
- Gunn, Philip, 1987 (Offsite-box 3753, Folder 12-13)
- Gunn, Philip [RESTRICTED], 1987 (Offsite-box R17)
- Management Meeting, 1987 April 2 (Offsite-box 3753, Folder 14)
- Personnel, 1987 (Offsite-box 3753, Folder 15)
- Personnel [RESTRICTED], 1987 (Offsite-box R17)
- Post Mortem, 1987 (Offsite-box 3753, Folder 16)
- Publicity Plan, 1980 (Offsite-box 3753, Folder 17)
- Publishing Review, 1987 (Offsite-box 3753, Folder 18)
- Re-estimates, 1986-1987 (Offsite-box 3753, Folder 19-20)
- Science 86 Acquisition, 1987 (Offsite-box 3753, Folder 21-23)
- Strategic Plan, 1983 (Offsite-box 3753, Folder 24)